# 哈喽大家好
Hi everyone
# 今天我跟我伯爷做一个苦瓜吃
Today I'm gonna cook a dish with the bitter gourd for my uncle
# 我们先把它的头去掉然后直接切成圈圈
Firstly we chop its head and cut it into rings directly
# 如果大家能够吃苦的话
If you are OK with bitter food
# 这个中间不用去得太干净
You don't have to remove all these at the center
# 如果不能吃苦的话就用刀把它刮干净一点
Otherwise, you can scrape it with a knife
# 苦瓜的苦味大部分是源自于这个里面
Most of the bitterness comes from this
# 这一层薄膜
The membrane here
# 其实苦瓜的籽是不苦的
Actually, the seeds of the bitter gourd are not bitter
# 主要是这一层白色的东西苦
It's the 'white membrane' that is bitter
# 这个东西热天吃了好
It's good to eat this in hot days
# 就是啊 吃的苦的话就不用整那么干净这个是下火的
That's right. If you eat bitter food, you don't need to remove it completely as it clears your 'internal heat'
# 清热
Clears the heat
# 是
Yep
# 好 这个我们就挖好了
Ok. We are done with this
# 但是这个苦瓜要先焯一下水
But we still need to blanch the bitter gourd first
# 焯完水之后放在凉水里面先泡一下
After blanching, soak it in cold water for a while
# 就是让它去除一些苦味
to remove some of the bitterness
# 还有就是让它更绿不变色
Also, this step keeps it green in the following cooking
# 我先拿去煮一下
Let me blanch it first
# 要的
Sure
# 好啦 这个我们已经焯过水啦
Ok. We've blanched this
# 直接把它放到凉水里面去泡一下
Let's soak it in cold water now
# 这样泡着它才不会变黄
In this way, it doesn't turn yellow
# 好啦 现在我们来切点肉
Ok. Now let's cut some meat
# 这个是五花肉先把它的皮去掉
Remove the skin of the pork belly first
# 然后我们把这个猪肉先切碎
Then cut the pork into slices first
# 切碎了之后再来剁成肉末
and mince it later
# 我们现在换双刀一起来把它剁一下
Let's use two cleavers together to chop it
# 剁得稍微细一些
Mince into fine pieces
# 我们这个肉还是最好用刀来剁
It's better to mince the meat with cleavers
# 刀剁出来的会比料理机搅碎的要好一些
The meat minced with cleavers is better than that minced with a grinder
# 好啦 我们这个肉就已经剁好啦
Ok. Now we've minced the meat
# 现在把它拿出来码一下味
It's time to season it
# 加一点点盐
Add a bit salt
# 然后加点胡椒粉
Some ground pepper
# 再加一点酱油
Some light soy sauce
# 然后加一点蚝油
Then some oyster sauce
# 再来加一点老抽调一下色
And some dark soy sauce for the color
# 好啦 加了这些之后把它拌匀
Done. Mix it up after adding all these
# 让这个盐充分的融合进去
To let the salt dissolve into the meat
# 打出一些胶质出来
Stir it until you feel some gel-like stuff #请检查这里
# 好 这个上劲了之后我们打一个鸡蛋进去
Ok. After the meat becomes sticky, add an egg into the bowl #这里上劲感觉不仅是粘，但是如果翻译成tough或者elastic之类好像也有点怪
# 打鸡蛋的话就让这个肉更嫩更有质感
Adding an egg makes the meat more tender and textured
# 给它拌匀
Mix it up again
# 好
Done
# 然后我们再放一点淀粉
Then add some starch
# 这个淀粉可以稍微的多一点点
We can add a bit more starch
# 因为要让这个肉重新回到一个粘手的一个状态
Because we need to make the meat sticky again
# 你看嘛 马上就粘手了
See? It becomes sticky immediately
# 是不是
Right?
# 是啊
Yeah
# 好 我们这个搅好啦
Ok. Now we are done with the mixing job
# 然后我们把这个苦瓜倒出来沥一下水
Then let's pour out the bitter gourd and drain the water
# 好啦现在我们来上一下干淀粉
Ok. Now apply some dry starch
# 我们先把这个干淀粉往中间抹一抹
Firstly apply some dry starch into the middle
# 它这个待会儿就可以很轻松的把肉粘上去了
Such that we can easily stuff the meat later
# 所说我们农村人整的东西没得那么好吃的
That's why the food in the countryside is not so delicious
# 你看你这个好麻烦哦
Look. Your dish is so complicated
# 然后这个盆里面的淀粉我们不要丢
Also, don't throw away the starch in this bowl
# 给它再放一点进去铺一下下面
Add some more starch to cover its bottom
# 给它铺在底下
Cover the bottom with the starch
# 然后这下又反过来
Then we exchange these two bowls
# 看嘛 看好麻烦嘛
See? So complicated
# 反过来又放肉进去
Exchange them and stuff the meat into the gourd
# 是啊
Yep
# 这样子
Like this
# 肉拿起来往中间放
Take some meat and stuff into the center
# 往中间放
Stuff into the center
# 放了肉之后再粘点淀粉
After stuffing, apply some more starch
# 两边都粘上淀粉就可以了
Apply starch to both sides
# 粘好了就这样放下去
Then just leave it there like this
# 为什么这下面我要垫粉呢
Why did I put some starch here?
# 就是因为这样放下去了之后就不会粘盘子
In this way, the meat won't stick to the plate
# 就是这个原因
That's the reason
# 我整一个来试一下
Let me have a try
# 嗯 可以啊
Ok. Sure
# 怎么样嘛
How is it?
# 这边再给它撒点淀粉
Apply some starch on this side
# 好 抹一下
Ok. Smear it
# 嗯 四伯爷做的不错
Good job, uncle
# 这边感觉淀粉少了点
I think the starch on this side is not enough
# 少了不关事这下面还垫得有
Don't worry. There's more at the bottom
# 要得呀
Ok
# 不关事
It doesn't matter
# 四伯爷除了杀猪那些还是多做些美食撒
Uncle, besides butchering pigs, what about cooking more delicious food?
# 我一个杀猪匠又何尝不想当个美食家嘛
As a butcher, why would I refuse to be a connoisseur?
# 我当个美食家的话我出去卖肉都要好卖点
Were I a connoisseur, I'd be able to sell more pork
# 给别人说这个肉该怎么做来吃
I'd tell my customers how to cook this cut of pork
# 那个肉该怎么做来吃
and how to cook that cut of pork
# 我的肉都要好卖得多
My pork will definitely sell better
# 嗯 就是
Yeah. Sure
# 好啦 现在我们来调一个汁 简单的
Ok. Now let's make a sauce. A simple one
# 放一点点盐 盐不能太多一点点就可以了
A bit salt. Don't add too much; a little salt will do the job
# 然后再放一点白糖
Then add some sugar
# 放一点点胡椒粉
A bit ground pepper
# 再放一点点料酒
Some Chinese cooking wine
# 还要放一点生抽酱油
And some light soy sauce
# 最后加一点蚝油
And some oyster sauce
# 我们再加一点清水
Add some water as well
# 最后加一点淀粉搅拌一下
Finally, add some starch and stir it
# 这个汁就调好了
The sauce is ready to go
# 待会儿我们这个苦瓜两边煎熟了之后
After frying both sides of the bitter gourd
# 直接倒这个进去收汁就可以出菜了
Pour this sauce into the wok, thicken it, and the dish is ready to serve!
# 特别简单的一道菜
This dish is really simple
# 我们到这一步的时候就慢慢给它煎
At this stage, fry it slowly
# 煎到这一面熟了之后再用筷子把它翻过来再煎另一面
When one side is well cooked, flip it with chopsticks and fry the other side
# 好 这面煎香了之后我们用筷子把它翻过来
Ok. Now this side smells good. Let's flip them with chopsticks
# 好 翻过来之后我们又继续煎
Ok. Continue frying the other side
# 煎到它熟香为止
Until it is well cooked and smells nice
# 好啦 感觉到这个有点焦香焦香的时候
Ok. When you smell a pleasant burnt scent
# 然后我们再给它翻过来看一下
Flip it over again and take a look
# 哇 已经煎得金黄了
Wow. It now looks gold
# 再给它翻一下
Flip it again
# 好啦 我们最后再煎2分钟
Okay. Fry for the last two more minutes
# 我们这个已经完全煎好啦
This is now completely done
# 现在把多余的油倒一点出来
Now let's pour out some excess oil
# 然后我们把这个汁倒下去
Then add the sauce into the wok
# 还是继续小火把这个汁水收浓就可以了
Still, use low heat to thicken the sauce
# 好 轻轻的翻一下就可以了
Ok. Just flip it again
# 好 可以上菜啦
Yeah. Ready to serve!
# 看着摆起是安逸
Looks nice when you present them on the plate!
# 亮增增的
Shiny and bright
# 香味你闻到没
Can you smell the aroma?
# 闻到了
Yeah
# 夹嘛 四伯爷
Pick one up, uncle
# 这种做法你在哪里学到的啊
Where did you learn how to cook this?
# 在外面跑江湖的时候学到的
When I was traveling around and trying to make a living out there
# 哦 以后我还是出去跑哈江湖看学得到这些技术不哦
Oh. I think I also need to travel around and see if I can learn these skills
# 可以啊
Sure
# 嗯 还有一点甜
Hmm. It's even a bit sweet
# 是不哦
Isn't it?
# 是啊
Yes
# 我还说苦 没想到还有点甜
I thought it would be bitter, but didn't expect to be sweet
# 加了点白糖都嘛
I added some sugar
# 也有点苦
A little bitter too
# 其实这样做的话比较香
Actually it tastes better in this way
# 煎出来的更香
Tastes better if fried slowly
# 但是在我们饭店里面一般是直接下去炸
But in restaurants, we usually just deep-fry it
# 或者是放到蒸柜里面蒸
Or steam it in a steamer
# 如果是蒸的话就颜色特别好看
It looks really nice if steamed
# 但是不香很苦
But not tasty. It'll be very bitter
# 我们这个煎出来的虽然说
The fried dish...
# 有点黄黄的
though looks brown in color
# 但是吃起来绝对很香绝对下饭
But is absolutely tasty and goes well with rice
# 嗯 安逸好香哦
Hmm. Nice! So tasty
# 这种做法我还是第一次吃
This is my first time to taste it
# 你吃在嘴里是什么感受嘛
How do you like it?
# 哎呀吃起安逸
Damn good. So nice
# 那个味道说不出来
I can't describe the flavor precisely
# 说不出来
Can't describe?
# 嗯
Yes
# 又有点甜
It's a bit sweet
# 又有点苦
and a little bitter
# 就是好吃嘛
Anyway, it's delicious
# 又有点香
And somewhat tasty
# 嘿嘿 还不好总结这个味道
Well. It's hard to summarize the taste
# 安逸
Nice!
# 这个苦瓜吃起还有点脆
The bitter gourd is a little crunchy
# 嗯
Yeah
# 这个吃了好下火的
This dish is healthy. It will clear out your 'internal heat'
# 我晓得这个苦瓜吃了好
I know it's good for the health
# 我这个才漂亮
This one here is beautiful
# 看嘛
Look
# 这个是你做的
Yeah. You made this one
# 看好安逸嘛
Look. It's so nice
# 好 本期视频就到这里啦
Ok. That's the end of this video
# 拜拜
Bye-bye!
# 好吃 我去添饭
Tasty. Let me get some rice